Engrave it...
刻吧
Engrave it upon your body.
刻在你身上
Engrave it upon the land.
刻在這片土地上
Engrave it upon the sea.
刻在大海上
Engrave it upon your enemy.
刻在敵人身上
Engrave it upon your loot.
刻在戰利品上
Engrave it...
刻吧
Engrave your warmth upon me.
把你的溫暖刻在我身上
Einar!
埃納爾
What was that for!
現在是怎樣?
Right back at you.
彼此彼此
If you cut that tree it'll crush our house.
你砍下那棵樹的話 我們的房子就毀了
- Are you going to become a woodcutter? - No, I'm not.
-你想成為伐木工嗎? -才不想
I'm training for battle! Take a look at my power!
我在為了上戰場做訓練 瞧瞧我的厲害
You may be well-built,
你的體格或許不錯
but that doesn't mean you can fight. Now get the food ready!
但那不表示你會作戰 去給我準備食物
I'm starving!
我餓死了
More like, don't throw a knife at me.
也不用拿刀子丟我吧
Pick something else like plates or spoons.
用盤子或湯匙就夠了吧
It's okay if it's a plate?
用盤子就沒事了嗎?
So that's why bears do it.
所以熊才會這麼做
- Eat a lot before winter. - Is that so.
-在冬季來臨之前拚命吃 -是喔?
- Thanks. - So, why did you?
-謝謝 -你是怎麼回事?
Start training all of a sudden?
突然之間開始訓練
What else is there, other than to protect this place.
還能有什麼原因? 為了保護這個村子啊
Everything was reduced to ashes.
原本一切都化為了灰燼
But we finally got back on our feet.
但我們終究讓一切回到正軌
Nobody wants to go through that again.
那種經歷,沒有任何人想再來一次
Even Dad--
連爸爸他...
Guttorm's milk is delicious!
古托姆的牛奶真好喝
I know, right? That man knows
我知道,對吧?那個人
how to handle teats.
很會擠奶
What's with those fingers? How creepy!
那些手指是怎麼回事?很嚇人
I'm talking here!
我正在說話!
- Ew! - Don't think about it.
-超噁 -別想那麼多了
Don't involve yourself with warriors.
別跟戰士攪和在一起
Aren't you frustrated with being on the losing end all the time?
一直輸,妳不覺得很厭煩嗎?
Dad died to protect us, you know.
爸為了保護我們而喪命,妳知道的
That's right. And that's why you're alive.
沒錯,這就是你還活著的原因
You rebuilt the village
你重建了這座村子
and are eating a delicious meal with two beauties.
還能和兩位美女一起享用美食
We haven't lost.
我們沒有輸
Listen, once you enter the forest, just run for your life.
聽好,一旦進入森林之後 就拚了命地跑
Follow the river...
沿著河流跑
Róta...
羅塔
Mom...
媽
Don't think about anything. Just run straight ahead.
什麼都別想,直直往前跑就對了
Your brother and mother are with you.
哥哥和媽媽會陪著妳
Mom!
媽
Ready? I'll lift you up.
準備好了嗎?我扶妳起來
Einar, run away.
埃納爾,快跑
- Leave me behind. - Don't be stupid!
-別管我了 -別說傻話
Forget that! Just try to stand up!
門都沒有,試著站著來就對了
Mom?
媽?
Mom!
媽
Stupid girl...
傻孩子
Hey, there are still people over there.
嘿,那裡還有人
Oh, I see a woman too. Here we come!
我見到了一個女人,快點過去吧
Stand up, Einar.
站起來,埃納爾
Take Róta... Hurry!
帶上羅塔,快點
Mom...
媽...
I may be a dying old lady...
我或許是個快死的老婦人
but I can do this much.
但我還有一口氣在
Make it out alive...
想辦法活下來
As long as you're alive...
只要你還活著
you can start again...
就能重新開始
Einar...
埃納爾
Róta...
羅塔
Why aren't they running away?
他們為什麼不逃跑?
Hey, she's pretty cute.
嘿,她長得滿可愛的
Your mama died, right?
你們的媽媽死了,對吧?
- Róta! - Let go!
-羅塔 -放手
- Einar! - Róta!
-埃納爾 -羅塔
Let go of her!
放開她
Einar!
埃納爾
I won't forgive you! How dare you!
我絕不會原諒你,你好大的膽子
- Einar! - How sad.
-埃納爾 -好可憐喲
How dare you--
你竟敢...
Hey! What are you doing?!
喂,你是怎麼搞的?
She stabbed me with something!
她用東西刺我!
What a waste.
真是糟蹋了
Oh well. Let's sell this kid and get some drinks with that money.
好吧,把這孩子賣了 我們拿錢買酒喝
- You're such an idiot! - I'm sorry, okay?
-你真是個笨蛋 -對不起嘛,可以吧?
Come on, drink money.
來吧,酒錢靠你了
A FIR TREE STANDING ON BARREN LAND DIES WITH NO BARK NOR LEAVES TO SHELTER IT
(一棵生長在貧瘠土地上的冷杉死了 沒有樹皮也沒有樹葉的保護)
SO IS A MAN WHOM NO ONE LOVES
(一個沒人愛的人也是如此)
WHY SHOULD HE KEEP ON LIVING? EXCERPT FROM HÁVAMÁL
(他為什麼還要繼續活著? 節錄自《海寇詩經》)
How is she?
她還好嗎?
This is no good.
情況不妙
Damn it.
該死
We have no choice. Help me carry her.
沒有別的辦法了,幫我把她抬起來
Ready...
準備...
Hey!
喂
Hey! What are you doing?!
喂,你們在做什麼?
You didn't have to throw her out!
沒必要把她丟下海吧?
Good, it's not inflamed.
很好,沒有發炎
We'll pass out fur blankets. Keep your bodies warm.
我們會發送毛毯,讓你們保暖
We spent a fortune on you all.
我們在你們身上花了一大筆錢
Don't you dare become sick without our approval.
沒有我們的允許,不准你們生病
At least stay healthy until we find a buyer for you. Got that?
至少在我們找到買家之前 要保持得健健康康,懂嗎?
Hurry up! We have to furl the sail!
快點,我們必須收帆了
That's right...
沒錯
I have to live...
我得活下去
Make sure to drink alcohol. It'll give you a healthy complexion.
一定要喝酒,會讓你們的氣色 看起來比較好
Wash every nook and cranny. Especially your hair.
把全身每個部位 洗得乾乾淨淨,尤其是頭髮
Get rid of each other's lice.
互相幫忙除蝨子
How is that?
這樣如何?
Her hair is fine. Do her makeup so she looks younger.
頭髮還可以,幫她化妝 讓她看起來年輕一點
How about it? We have a pretty good lineup, don't we?
不錯吧?我們的人選 相當吸引人,對吧?
They're all so-so.
全都普普通通
Don't say that. We have the best of the best.
別這麼說嘛,我們有上等的貨色
That's right... I can't just stay there!
沒錯,我不能坐以待斃
If I can get out of here alive, I can start again...
只要我能活著離開這裡 我就能重新開始
Up we go...
來吧
A thief!
小偷!
Sorry!
對不起
Hey, Einar.
嗨,埃納爾
It seems like you still don't get it.
看來你仍然搞不清楚狀況
All right, you slaves. Listen carefully.
好的,你們這群奴隸,給我仔細聽好
Your homelands are far, far away.
你們的家鄉離這裡很遙遠
You can't return even if you try.
你們想盡辦法也回不去了
And of course, no one will help you run away.
當然啦,沒有人會幫你們逃跑
That's because you're foreign, penniless,
因為你們是來自異地、身無分文的
slaves!
奴隸
Get someone nice to buy you and do your best to serve them.
替自己找個好買家吧 然後好好地服侍他們
You'll get to eat nice meals, which you won't if you escape and become a beggar.
你們就能夠三餐溫飽 逃跑之後成了乞丐,就沒這種福氣囉
Before you venture out, think about which life is more favorable.
在你們行動之前 先想清楚哪一種生活比較好
Got that, Einar?
懂嗎,埃納爾?
I...
我...
will...
一定會...
...live!
活下去
Yeah...
這個嘛...
He's not bad,
他還不錯
but don't you have one with a cuter face?
但你沒有長相可愛一點的嗎?
I see! If that's the case,
了解,如果是這樣的話...
I have a special one just for you.
我特地幫你準備了一個特別人選
Is that so? How exciting.
是嗎?我好興奮喔
I'm sure you will love it.
我肯定你會喜歡
They are right.
他們說的沒錯
Even if I recklessly escape
就算我不顧一切地逃跑
I won't have anyone to help me.
我也無法找到幫助我的人
Besides...
況且...
I don't...
我...
have anywhere to go anymore.
已經成了無家可歸的人
If I just...
如果我...
give in and become an obedient pet...
就這樣屈服,當個順從的寵物...
My goodness, you sure are lucky.
我的天,你真的運氣很好
We just restocked a bunch of them.
我們才剛剛來了一批新貨色
Look, that's him.
你看,就是他
He's what you're looking for, right?
他就是你想要的人,對吧?
He's completely different!
才不是你說的那樣!
He's neither blond nor small!
他不是金髮、也不嬌小
How weird... Now that I take a good look, he's not.
這就奇怪了 我現在仔細看了一下,的確是如此
Well, anyhow, what do you think about him?
總而言之,你覺得他怎麼樣?
He's strong and sturdy. If you buy now--
他很強壯又健康 如果你現在出價的話...
Like I said, I'm not here to buy a worker!
我說過了,我不是來買工人的
I just want to free a relative of mine.
我只是想要解放一位我的親戚
I'm pretty sure he ended up in this town.
我相當肯定他來到了這個鎮上
He's blond and small and his name is Thorfinn.
他有一頭金髮,而且個頭嬌小 他的名字是托爾芬
Are you sure you have no clue where he is?
你確定你不知道他在哪裡嗎?
Sorry about that.
抱歉了
Sorry to waste your time.
抱歉浪費你的時間
No worries. Please come again.
沒事啦,下次再來喔
He'll never find him.
他絕對找不到他的
So he's asking around in search of his relative, huh?
原來他在四處詢問親戚的下落啊?
Whoever has someone like that searching for him
能夠有個像他這樣 四處尋找自己下落的親戚
is so fortunate.
那個人實在很幸運
You there.
喂,你
Can you understand me? Show me your teeth.
聽得懂我說的話嗎? 給我看看你的牙齒
- What's your name? - It's Einar.
-你叫什麼名字? -埃納爾
Where are you from and what was your profession?
你是哪裡人?做什麼的?
I was a farmer in the north of England.
我是來自於北英格蘭的農夫
Einar, what do you think about helping out with my field?
埃納爾,來幫我種田,你意下如何?
Field?
種田?
Einar, this way!
埃納爾,這裡
All of my servants are working now.
我所有的僕人都在工作
- I'll introduce you during dinnertime. - Yes, sir.
-晚餐時間,我再把你介紹給大家 -好的,主人
First, take a look at my farm.
首先,看看我的農地吧
Hey, Mom, are you sure?
媽,妳確定嗎?
I don't even have the freedom to choose
我連選擇是生是死的
life or death anymore.
權力都沒有
Can you still say
妳仍然能夠說...
that we haven't lost?
我們沒輸嗎?
My family was killed
我的家人被殺害了
and I lost everything including my homeland.
我失去了一切,包括我的家園
I didn't even know
我甚至不知道
what I was living for.
我還活著幹嘛?
Thorfinn! It's me! Can you come out?
托爾芬,是我,出來好嗎?
I must be bought by a kind master
我一定要讓一位好主人買下我
and do my very best to serve him.
盡我所能地服侍他
As long as I stay obedient, I won't go hungry.
只要我事事順從,我就不會挨餓
I was starting to believe that.
我開始相信這件事了
Thorfinn?
托爾芬?
In any case,
總之...
that was when I met Thorfinn for the first time.
那是我第一次見到托爾芬
"Ketil's farm."
凱特爾的農場
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯:歐德慧